Almost a year ago,
منذ سنة تقريبا،
my aunt started suffering back pains.
بدأت عمتي تعاني من آلام في الظهر.
She went to see the doctor
ذهبت لرؤية الطبيب
and they told her it was a normal injury
وأخبرها بأنه أمر عادي
for someone who had been playing tennis
لشخص مارس كرة المضرب
for almost 30 years.
لما يقرب 30 سنة.
They recommended that she do some therapy,
وأوصاها بتتبع بعض العلاجات،
but after a while she wasn't feeling better,
لكنها لم تشعر بتحسن،
so the doctors decided to do further tests.
فقرر الأطباء إخضاعها لفحوصات معمقة.
They did an x-ray
فكشفت الأشعة السينية عن ضرر في رئتيها،
and at the time they thought that the injury
وقد اعتقدوا في البداية أن الضرر
was a strain in the muscles and tendons
كان مجرد إجهاد بالعضلات والأوتار
between her ribs,
الوربية،
but after a few weeks of treatment,
لكن بعد بضعة أسابيع من العلاج،
again her health wasn't getting any better.
لم تتحسن حالتها مرة أخرى.
So finally, they decided to do a biopsy,
في النهاية، قرر الأطباء القيام بخزعة،
and two weeks later,
وبعد أسبوعين،
the results of the biopsy came back.
ظهرت نتائج الخزعة.
It was stage 3 lung cancer.
كان سرطان الرئة، في المرحلة 3.
Her lifestyle was almost free of risk.
كانت طريقة عيشها خالية من المخاطر تقريبا.
She never smoked a cigarette,
لم تدخن قط،
she never drank alcohol,
لم تشرب الكحول من قبل،
and she had been playing sports
وكانت تمارس الرياضة
for almost half her life.
لما يقارب نصف عمرها.
Perhaps, that is why it took them almost six months
وربما كان هذا هو السبب الذي أخر الأطباء
My story might be, unfortunately,
على الأرجح أن معظمكم، مع الآسف،
familiar to most of you.
قد عاش قصة كقصتي هذه.
One out of three people sitting in this audience
واحد من كل 3 أشخاص من الحاضرين هنا
will be diagnosed with some type of cancer,
سيشخص لديه نوع من أنواع السرطان،
and one out of four
وواحد من أصل 4
will die because of it.
سيتوفى بسببه.
Not only did that cancer diagnosis
لم يقم تشخيص سرطان عمتي
change the life of our family,
بتغيير حياة عائلتنا وحسب،
but that process of going
بل إن عملية الانتقال من اختبار
back and forth with new tests,
إلى اختبار جديد،
different doctors describing symptoms,
بين عدة أطباء يصفون الأعراض،
discarding diseases over and over,
واستبعاد مرض بعد الآخر،
was stressful and frustrating,
كان أمرا مرهقا ومحبطا،
especially for my aunt.
وخاصة بالنسبة لعمتي.
And that is the way cancer diagnosis has been done
وكانت هذه هي طريقة تشخيص السرطان
since the beginning of history.
منذ بداية التاريخ.
We have 21st-century medical treatments and drugs
لدينا اليوم علاجات طبية وأدوية
to treat cancer,
لعلاج السرطان من القرن 21،
but we still have 20th-century procedures
لكن ما زلنا نعمل بإجراءات القرن 20
and processes for diagnosis, if any.
في التشخيص، وهذا إن وجدت.
Today, most of us have to wait for symptoms
حاليا، على معظمنا انتظار الأعراض
to indicate that something is wrong.
لتعلمه بأن هناك شيئا خطأ.
Today, the majority of people still don't have access
ومازال أغلب الناس لا يصلون
to early cancer detection methods,
لطرق التشخيص المبكرة للسرطان،
even though we know
حتى وإن علمنا بأن التشخيص المبكر للسرطان
is basically the closest thing we have
هو أفضل طريقة لدينا لعلاجه.
We know that we can change this in our lifetime,
ونحن نعلم بأنه يمكننا تغيير ذلك،
and that is why my team and I
وهذا هو الدافع الذي جعلني وفريقي
have decided to begin this journey,
نقرر الانطلاق في هذه الرحلة،
this journey to try to make cancer detection
رحلة لمحاولة جعل تشخيص السرطان
at the early stages
في مراحله المبكرة
and monitoring the appropriate response at the molecular level
ورصد الاستجابة المناسبة على المستوى الجزيئي
easier, cheaper, smarter
أسهل وأرخص وأذكى
and more accessible than ever before.
والوصول إليها أيسر من ذي قبل.
The context, of course,
السياق، بطبيعة الحال،
is that we're living at a time
هو أننا نعيش في عصر
where technology is disrupting our present
تسيطر فيه التقنية على حاضرنا
at exponential rates,
بسرعة فائقة،
and the biological realm is no exception.
والمجال البيولوجي ليس استثناءً.
It is said today that biotech is advancing
يقال اليوم بأن التقانة الحيوية تتطور
at least six times faster than the growth rate
على الأقل 6 مرات أسرع من معدل تطور
of the processing power of computers.
معالجات الحواسيب.
But progress in biotech
لكن التطور في التقانة الحيوية
is not only being accelerated,
لا يقتصر فقط على سرعة التطور،
it is also being democratized.
بل أيضا على دمقرطتها.
Just as personal computers or the Internet
تماما كما الحواسيب الشخصية أو الانترنيت
or smartphones leveled the playing field
أو الهواتف الذكية التي توفر فرصا متكافئة
for entrepreneurship, politics or education,
في مجال الأعمال والسياسة والتعليم،
and that is allowing
وهذا يسمح
multidisciplinary teams like ours
لفرق متعددة التخصصات مثلنا
to try to tackle and look at these problems
لمحاولة الانكباب على هذه المشاكل
with new approaches.
بمقاربة جديدة.
We are a team of scientists and technologists
نحن فريق من العلماء والتقنيين
from Chile, Panama,
من تشيلي وبناما
Mexico, Israel and Greece,
والمكسيك وإسرائيل واليونان،
and based on recent scientific discoveries,
ونعتقد أنه بناء على الاكتشافات العلمية الأخيرة
we believe that we have found
بأننا وجدنا
a reliable and accurate way
طريقة موثوقة ودقيقة
of detecting several types of cancer
للكشف عن أنواع عديدة من السرطان
at the very early stages through a blood sample.
في المراحل المبكرة من عينة الدم.
We do it by detecting a set of very small molecules
وذلك بالكشف عن مجموعة من الجزيئات الصغيرة
that circulate freely in our blood
التي تدور بكل حرية مع الدم
called microRNAs.
والمسماة بالميكرو رنا.
To explain what microRNAs are
ولكي أشرح لكم ما هي الميكرو رنا
and their important role in cancer,
وما علاقتها بالسرطان،
I need to start with proteins,
سأحتاج للبروتينات،
because when cancer is present in our body,
لأنه عند الإصابة بالسرطان،
protein modification is observed
يلاحظ حدوث تغيرات في البروتين
in all cancerous cells.
في جميع الخلايا السرطانية.
As you might know,
وكما قد تعلمون،
proteins are large biological molecules
البروتينات هي جزيئات حيوية
that perform different functions within our body,
تقوم بوظائف مختلفة في الجسم،
like catalyzing metabolic reactions
كتحفيز التفاعلات الأيضية
or responding to stimuli
أو الاستجابة للمحفزات
or replicating DNA,
أو إعادة إنتاج الحمض النووي،
but before a protein is expressed or produced,
لكن قبل تركيب البروتين أو إنتاجه،
relevant parts of its genetic code
فإن أجزاء مهمة من شفرته الوراثية
present in the DNA
الموجودة في الحمض النووي
are copied into the messenger RNA,
تنسخ داخل حامل الميكرو رنا،
so this messenger RNA
ويمتلك هذا الحامل
has instructions on how to build a specific protein,
تعليمات حول كيفية تركيب بروتين معين،
and potentially it can build hundreds of proteins,
ويحتمل أنه قادر على تركيب المئات منها،
but the one that tells them when to build them
لكن المسؤول الذي يخبره متى يقوم بتركيبها
and how many to build
وبالعدد الذي سيركبه
are microRNAs.
هو الميكرو رنا.
So microRNAs are small molecules
الميكرو رنا هي جزيئات صغيرة
that regulate gene expression.
مُنَظِّمة للتعبير الوراثي.
Unlike DNA, which is mainly fixed,
عكس الحمض النووي الثابت،
microRNAs can vary depending on internal
فإنه يمكن للميكرو رنا أن تتأثر في أي وقت
and environmental conditions at any given time,
بالظروف الداخلية والمحيطة به،
And that is what makes microRNAs
وهذا ما يجعل من الميكرو رنا
such a promising biomarker for cancer,
علامة بيولوجية واعدة للكشف عن السرطان،
because as you know,
لأنه وكما تعلمون،
cancer is a disease of altered gene expression.
السرطان هو تشوه في التعبير الوراثي.
It is the uncontrolled regulation of genes.
هو تنظيم غير منضبط للمورثات.
Another important thing to consider
الأمر الآخر المهم الذي ينبغي اعتباره
is that no two cancers are the same,
هو أنه لا يوجد نوعان متشابهان من السرطان،
but at the microRNA level, there are patterns.
لكن على مستوى الميكرو رنا، هناك بصمات.
Several scientific studies have shown
لقد أثبتت عدة دراسات علمية
that abnormal microRNA expression levels
بأن مستويات التعبير اللاطبيعي للميكرو رنا
varies and creates a unique, specific pattern
يختلف ويخلق بصمة فريدة ومحددة
for each type of cancer,
لكل نوع من السرطان،
even at the early stages,
حتى في مراحله الأولى،
reflecting the progression of the disease,
عاكسة بذلك تطور المرض،
and whether it's responding to medication
وسواء كان ذلك من حيث تفاعله مع العلاج
or in remission,
أو في الهدأة،
making microRNAs a perfect,
وهذا يجعل من الميكرو رنا أفضل،
highly sensitive biomarker.
وأكثر العلامات البيولوجية حساسية.
However, the problem with microRNAs
لكن مشكل الميكرو رنا
to detect them in a reliable way,
للكشف عنها بطريقة موثوقة،
because they are very short sequences of nucleotides,
لأنها سلاسل جد قصيرة من النيوكليوتيدات،
much smaller than DNA.
أصغر من الحمض النووي.
And also, all microRNAs are very similar to each other,
كما أن كل الميكرو نار متشابهة،
with just tiny differences.
مع فوارق ضئيلة.
So imagine trying to differentiate two molecules,
تصوروا محاولة التفريق بين جزيئين،
extremely similar, extremely small.
متشابهين وصغيرين للغاية.
We believe that we have found a way to do so,
ونعتقد بأننا وجدنا طريقة القيام بذلك،
and this is the first time that we've shown it in public.
وهذه أول مرة نقوم بعرضها على الملأ.
Let me do a demonstration.
دعوني أعرضها أمامكم.
and do your next standard blood test,
للقيام بفحصكم الاعتيادي للدم،
a lab technician extracts a total RNA,
فيأخذ التقني عينة رنا كاملة،
which is quite simple today,
التي أصبحت اليوم أمرا سهلا،
and puts it in a standard 96-well plate like this one.
ويضعها على صفيحة 96 بئر كهذه.
Each well of these plates
حيث تحتوي كل بئر من هذه الصفائح
has specific biochemistry that we assign,
على عامل كيمائي حيوي محدد،
that is looking for a specific microRNA,
يتفاعل مع ميكرو رنا محددة،
acting like a trap that closes
أي أنها تشبه تقريبا فخا
only when the microRNA is present in the sample,
يمسك فقط بالميكرو رنا الموجودة في العينة،
and when it does, it will shine with green color.
وعندما يقوم بذلك، سيتلون بالأخضر.
To run the reaction,
وللقيام بالفحص،
you put the plate inside a device like this one,
ما عليكم سوى وضع الصفيحة في جهاز كهذا،
and then you can put your smartphone on top of it.
ثم تضعون هاتفكم الذكي في الأعلى.
If we can have a camera here
أرجو تقريب الكاميرا من هنا
so you can see my screen.
لنتمكن من مشاهدة العملية عن قرب.
A smartphone is a connected computer
الهاتف الذكي هو حاسوب متصل
and it's also a camera,
وهو أيضا آلة تصوير
good enough for our purpose.
جيدة بما يكفي للقيام بما نرغب فيه.
The smartphone is taking pictures,
يلتقط الهاتف الصور،
and when the reaction is over,
وعند انتهاء الفحص،
it will send the pictures
سيرسل الصور
to our online database for processing
إلى قاعدة بياناتنا على الإنترنت للمعالجة
and interpretation.
والتشخيص.
This entire process lasts around 60 minutes,
وتستغرق العملية حوالي 60 دقيقة،
but when the process is over,
وفي نهايتها،
wells that shine are matched with the specific microRNAs
تطابق الآبار الملونة مع ميكرو رنا محددة
and analyzed in terms of how much and how fast
وتحلل وفقا لمدى ولسرعة
they shine.
تلونها.
And then, when this entire process is over,
وبعد انتهاء العملية بالكامل،
this is what happens.
فإن هذا ما نحصل عليه.
This chart is showing the specific microRNAs
هذا الجدول يبين لنا الميكرو رنا
present in this sample
المتواجدة في العينة
and how they reacted over time.
وعن سرعة تفاعلها خلال الفحص.
Then, if we take this specific pattern of microRNA
وإن أخذنا هذه الميكرو رنا النموذج
of this person's samples
من عينات لهذا الشخص
and compare it with existing scientific documentation
وقارناها بالوثائق العلمية الموجودة
that correlates microRNA patterns
المتعلقة بأنماط الميكرو رنا
with a specific presence of a disease,
المرتبطة بأمراض محددة،
this is how pancreatic cancer looks like.
هذا ما سيبدو عليه سرطان البنكرياس.
This inside is a real sample
العينة بالداخل حقيقية،
where we just detected pancreatic cancer.
وقد تمكنا للتو من تشخيص سرطان البنكرياس.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Another important aspect of this approach
الأهمية الأخرى لهذه المقاربة
is the gathering and mining of data in the cloud,
هو تجميع واستخراج البيانات من السحابة،
so we can get results in real time
حيث نحصل على النتائج في الوقت الحقيقي
and analyze them with our contextual information.
ونحللها وفقا لمعطياتنا السياقية.
If we want to better understand
إن أردنا أن نفهم بشكل أفضل
and decode diseases like cancer,
وأن نفك شيفرة أمراض كالسرطان،
we need to stop treating them
سنحتاج للتوقف على اعتبارها
as acute, isolated episodes,
كمراحل خطيرة ومعزولة في حياتنا،
and consider and measure everything
واعتبار وتقييم كل شيء
that affects our health on a permanent basis.
يؤثر في صحتنا بشكل مستمر.
This entire platform is a working prototype.
إن هذا المنهاج في العمل هو أنموذج.
It uses state-of-the-art molecular biology,
يستخدم آخر تقنيات البيولوجية الجزيئية،
a low-cost, 3D-printed device,
طابعة ثلاثية الأبعاد بخسة الثمن،
and data science
وقاعدة بيانات علمية كمحاولة
to try to tackle one of humanity's toughest challenges.
لمواجهة واحدة من أكبر تحديات البشرية.
Since we believe early cancer detection
وبما أننا نؤمن بضرورة
should really be democratized,
دمقرطة الكشف المبكر للسرطان،
this entire solution costs at least 50 times less
فإن تكلفة الفحص أقل بـ 50 مرة على الأقل
than current available methods,
من طرق الفحص المتوفرة حاليا،
and we know that the community can help us
وإيمانا منا بأن المجتمع العلمي سيساعدنا
accelerate this even more,
في تسريع وتيرة تطويره،
so we're making the design of the device
جعلنا تصميم هذا الجهاز
open-source.
مفتوح المصدر.
Let me say very clearly
دعوني أخبركم وبشكل واضح
that we are at the very early stages,
بأننا ما نزال في المراحل الأولى،
but so far, we have been able
ورغم ذلك، نجحنا
to successfully identify the microRNA pattern
في التعرف على نمط من الميكرو رنا
of pancreatic cancer, lung cancer,
لسرطان البنكرياس والرئة
breast cancer and hepatic cancer.
والثدي والكبد.
And currently, we're doing a clinical trial
وحاليا، نقوم بتجربة سريرية
in collaboration with the German Cancer Research Center
بالتعاون مع المركز الألماني لأبحاث السرطان
with 200 women for breast cancer.
على 200 امرأة لسرطان الثدي.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
This is the single non-invasive,
وهو الاختبار الوحيد الغَيرُ باضِع
accurate and affordable test
والدقيق وذي التكلفة المعقولة
that has the potential to dramatically change
الذي يمكنه إحداث تغيير كبير
how cancer procedures and diagnostics
في كيفية القيام بإجراءات
have been done.
وتشخيصات السرطان.
Since we're looking for the microRNA patterns
ولكوننا نبحث عن أنماط الميكرو رنا
in your blood at any given time,
في الدم في أي وقت،
you don't need to know which cancer you're looking for.
نوع السرطان الذي تبحثون عنه.
You don't need to have any symptoms.
لن تنتظروا ظهور أية أعراض.
You only need one milliliter of blood
ستحتاجون فقط لملليتر واحد من الدم
and a relatively simple array of tools.
ومجموعة بسيطة نسبيا من الأدوات.
Today, cancer detection happens mainly
حاليا، أغلب تشخيصات السرطان
when symptoms appear.
تتم عند ظهور الأعراض.
That is, at stage 3 or 4,
أي في المرحلة 3 أو 4،
and I believe that is too late.
وأعتقد بأن هذا تشخيص جد متأخر.
It is too expensive for our families.
وجد مكلف لأسرنا.
It is too expensive for humanity.
وجد مكلف للبشرية.
We cannot lose the war against cancer.
لا يمكننا أن نخسر الحرب ضد السرطان.
It not only costs us billions of dollars,
لأنه لا يكلفنا فقط مليارات الدولارات،
but it also costs us the people we love.
بل يكلفنا الأشخاص الذين نحبهم.
Today, my aunt, she's fighting bravely
اليوم، عمتي، تقاتل بشجاعة
and going through this process with a very positive attitude.
وتتقدم في علاجها بروح إيجابية.
However, I want fights like this
لكن، أملي أن يصبح القتال بهذا الشكل
to become very rare.
أمرا نادرا.
I want to see the day
أود أن أشهد اليوم
when cancer is treated easily
الذي سنتعامل فيه مع السرطان بسهولة
because it can be routinely diagnosed
لأن تشخيصه في مراحله المتقدمة
at the very early stages,
سيكون أمرا روتينيا،
and I'm certain
وأنا متأكد
that in the very near future,
بأنه في المستقبل القريب،
because of this
وبفضل هذا الفحص وغيره
and other breakthroughs that we are seeing
من الأفكار التي تزهر
every day in the life sciences,
كل يوم في المجالات العلمية،
the way we see cancer
فإن نظرتنا تجاه السرطان
will radically change.
ستتغير بشكل جذري.
It will give us the chance of detecting it early,
ستقدم لنا فرصة اكتشافه مبكرا،
understanding it better,
وفهمه بشكل أفضل،
and finding a cure.
وإيجاد العلاج.
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلا لكم.